<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-01T13:01:51-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lux Miranda</title><subtitle>Lux Miranda homepage</subtitle><author><name>Lux Miranda</name></author><entry><title type="html">The two types of society: Recurrent social formations and the quest to categorize</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/articles/2020/05/13/post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The two types of society: Recurrent social formations and the quest to categorize" /><published>2020-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/articles/2020/05/13/post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/articles/2020/05/13/post.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@blahji&quot;&gt;Balaji Malliswamy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human social diversity—ostensibly infinite in its intricacies—may in fact have more finite bounds than previously thought. Cross-culturally and throughout time, it seems that societies repeatedly form into one of two broad “types” in terms of social-ecological configuration – what have come to be known as &lt;em&gt;recurrent social formations&lt;/em&gt;. At least, that is what is indicated by an emerging body of research (including &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0232609&quot;&gt;my recent study published in &lt;em&gt;PLOS One&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; along with my co-author, Dr. Jacob Freeman).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social scientists have long attempted to place societies into neatly delineated categories. In anthropology, the endeavour is as old as the science itself. It dates back to at least as early as the typology put forth by the 1871 book &lt;em&gt;Primitive Culture&lt;/em&gt; wherein cultural evolutionist Edward Burnett Tylor posits that all societies pass through three basic stages of development: “savagery,” on to “barbarism,” and, finally, “civilization.” Given that Tylor’s definition of “civilization” was essentially limited to Victorian England and Similar but Obviously Lesser Societies, people eventually saw the (very racist) issues with this idea and cultural evolution was more-or-less discredited for nearly half a century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon its resurgence in the mid twentieth-century, social scientists again returned to the labeling and naming game in attempt to better conceptualize the landscape of human social diversity. Some of these are still used today. I (and most everyone else who has taken an introductory anthropology course) have learned at least a few schema for roughly dividing up cultures: the gradient of increasing political complexity that is “bands,” “tribes,” “chiefdoms,” and “states,” for example, or perhaps the division by subsistence strategy into “foragers,” “horticulturalists,” “pastoralists,” and “agriculturalists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, these categorizations serve only as rough conceptual approximations rather than any sort of useful typology. How shall we categorize historical Cahokia at its height, which certainly seems more than a chiefdom but.. Less than a state? And what of the Ju|‘hoansi, who traditionally subsist on foraging but now, under pressures from their government, also take up agricultural jobs at cattle ranches? I’m far from the first to point out the flaws with these schema, yet they continue to persist in the consciousness of social researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-05-13/Cahokia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cahokia&quot; style=&quot;display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cahokia, pearl of the Midwest&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s different now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of recurrent social formations turns this labeling practice on its head. Rather than looking at the details of cultures and attempting to infer broader structures, we’re able to look at the broad structures themselves and attempt to infer cultural details. Only in recent years has it become practical to do this; it requires researchers to leverage large-scale datasets of empirical, quantitative information on societies. Only gradually have datasets like this begun to appear. But, as they have, and as we have peered into the shapes of these data, interesting things have shown their faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore these shapes, we first need to define what we mean by the “shape” of the data. We consider each society at a particular time as a single data point. Each feature of that society is plotted along a new dimension, be it, for example, its territory size, number of levels in its religious hierarchy, or the complexity of its writing system. Of course, societies have more than three features; depending on the dataset, we might be dealing with something like 50-dimensional or 100-dimensional space. We can calculate the euclidean distances between each society in this space to detect if there’s any “clumping” of the data points (i.e., societal characteristics tending to gather near each other in certain pockets of space rather than being evenly spread out). And clumping is exactly what we see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Peregrine, in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfipress.org/books/emergence-of-premodern-states&quot;&gt;2018 book chapter &lt;em&gt;Toward a Theory of Recurrent Social Formations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was perhaps the first to discover the shape of societies in this space. Using societal data contained in the &lt;em&gt;Atlas of Cultural Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, Peregrine found “ridges” of clusters in the dataset using morphospace analysis. My cluster analysis, conducted on similar but disparate data in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://seshatdatabank.info/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seshat: Global History Databank&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, confirms the structures that Peregrine found and elucidates some of the shared features between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-05-13/Peregrine.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-05-13/Clusters.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of our analyses, there appear to be two large superclusters consisting of a few smaller clusters within. The above figures are visualizations of these from our respective studies. To visualize them, we aggregate every societal feature into one of just two axes: a “scale” axis (consisting of variables such as population, territory size, and social hierarchies) and a “non-scale” axis (consisting of variables concerning government, infrastructure, writing, and economy). Plotting the data in this way, one may easily see the two superclusters that societies clump together in (which I quite un-inspiredly refer to as the lower-complexity Supercluster A and the higher-complexity Supercluster B).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so here we have it: a typology of societies that shows itself, empirically, irrespective of the dataset or methods we use to look at it. I can definitively tell you that Old Kingdom Egypt and Cahokia at its height are both Supercluster A societies, whereas the Italian Papal States and Qing dynasty China are both Supercluster B societies, without any overlap whatsoever. Distinct categorizations! But, what does this mean? Well, I’m not entirely sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What absolutely fascinates me about this typology, however, becomes evident when we consider how societies move between clusters over time. Over thousands of years, societies in a single geographical area will often traverse through the entire range of possible clusters. When we take a closer look these time series, a few things strike out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2020-05-13/ParisBasin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cluster time series for the Paris Basin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The cluster time series for Paris Basin. Clusters 0 and 1 correspond to Supercluster A, Clusters 3 and 4 correspond to Supercluster B, and Cluster 2 represents a transitional state. PC1 is an additional metric measuring overall &quot;social complexity&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When societies enter Supercluster B, they almost &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; leave. What’s more is that societies transitioning from Supercluster A to Supercluster B don’t do so gradually, at a steady pace–rather, we see a rapid jump in social complexity, with many complex societal features all evolving at once, together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To borrow terms from evolutionary biology, we’re not seeing evidence of &lt;em&gt;gradualism&lt;/em&gt; but of &lt;em&gt;punctuated equilibrium&lt;/em&gt; in the evolution of cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I speak of these changes happening rapidly, of course, I do mean at the scale of centuries. Societies will remain in individual clusters long periods of time—sometimes thousands of years—but “jump” into Supercluster B over the course of just 200-300 years. (Incidentally, this is also the approximate time period for one full revolution of one of Turchin’s secular cycles, but this is wild speculation on my part).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What exactly is the impetus that springboards societies from the low-complexity Supercluster A to the high-complexity Supercluster B remains a mystery. Some initial analysis indicates that the answer &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be the development of a full writing system, but it is yet to be determined whether this is a causal factor or if a full writing system is just yet another feature that quickly evolves along with the overall jump in complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another hypothesis of mine is this: in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1043-4&quot;&gt;a 2019 &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; Article&lt;/a&gt;, Harvey Whitehouse and colleagues found that &lt;em&gt;large increases in social complexity&lt;/em&gt; precede the development of “moralizing gods” (i.e., supernatural entities that threaten punishment for not behaving pro-socially) throughout world history. I suspect that these “large increases” may correspond with shifts in cluster membership, but I’ve yet to test this. If it is the case, it may help shed light on the mechanisms that keep Supercluster B held together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to work out what exactly the forces are that drive these recurrent social formations to form. Only now that we have confidently identified them can we begin to understand what makes them tick. It is my hope that understanding what these dynamics are and how they’ve shaped human societies in the past will give us a greater understanding of the dynamics that govern our own societies today. With such knowledge, the goal is to be able to work the dynamics to our advantage in order to guide our own societies along more peaceful, prosperous, and sustainable paths. It goes without saying that the need for this grows ever more dire with each passing day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lux Miranda</name></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">Human social diversity—ostensibly infinite in its intricacies—may in fact have more finite bounds than previously thought. Cross-culturally and throughout time, it seems that societies repeatedly form into one of two broad &quot;types&quot; in terms of social configuration...</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/2020-05-13/temple.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/2020-05-13/temple.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>